

#### Contact

+92-331-7238425

zohaibhassan425@gmail.com

Linkedin.com/in/zohaib-hassan

House#1177, Q-Block, Johar Town, Lahore, Pakistan

#### **Education**

**MBA** - Marketing

Gov. College University Faisalabad 2014 - 2016

#### **B-Com**

Gov. College of Commerce Mianwali 2010 - 2012

#### **Expertise**

Import regulations, customs laws, and trade compliance

**Export Facilities Scheme, SRO 492** 

**Technology Proficiency** 

Logistic Management

**Team Management** 

Cost analysis and saving

Proficient in MS Office applications, ERP and SAP.

#### Language

English

Urdu

#### Interest

**Food Travelling** 

Music

### **ZOHAIB HASSAN**

Imports & Logistics

### **Professional Summary**

Accomplished professional with 11 years of experience in imports, logistics and procurement operations. Demonstrated leadership abilities, strategic planning expertise and problem-solving acumen. Assists senior management with accomplishing demanding targets by encouraging staff and coordinating resources. Methodical and well-organized in optimizing coverage to meet operational demands.

### **Career Objectives**

To contribute towards the growth and development of a dynamic organization where there are plenty of opportunities to grow professionally and personally and where I can utilize my skills and experience efficiently and effectively.

#### **Experience**



Import Specialist
Kohat Cement Company Limited
Jul 2023 - Present

- Manage entire import process including documentation, customs clearance, logistics, and compliance with international trade regulations.
- Liaise with suppliers, vendors, shipping agencies, and freight forwarders to ensure timely and cost-effective transportation of goods.
- Work closely with other departments, such as procurement, marketing and finance, to ensure a smooth import process.
- Stay informed about changes in import/export regulations and trade agreements that may impact the organization's import operations.
- Negotiate contracts, terms, and pricing with suppliers, ensuring favorable agreements and cost-effective sourcing.
- Manage and lead a team, conduct regular training sessions for the team to stay updated on changes in import/export laws.
- Ensure compliance with international trade regulations, customs requirements, and documentation standards, including the preparation of necessary permits and licenses.
- Handle any issues or discrepancies that may arise during the import process, including customs inspections or shipment delays.
- Plan, coordinate, and optimize transportation routes to ensure timely delivery of goods. Monitor and track shipments to ensure they arrive on schedule.
- Select appropriate carriers, shipping methods, and logistics providers based on cost, efficiency, and reliability.



## Dy. Manager Imports Sarena Textile Industries Private Limited Oct 2020- Jun 2023

- Manage imports of goods and ensure compliance to organizational policies and procedures.
- Planning with MMC and marketing team to finalize timeline of ordered goods.
- Collaborate with internal and external partners to limit costs and risks in the supply chain while also driving process improvements.
- Well know to activities related to Export Facilitation Scheme EFS, arrange custom clearance under EFS and SRO 492, Responsible to manage record of EFS and SRO 492.
- Coordination and follow up of suppliers for readiness and on-time deliveries based on production schedule.
- Design and implement import strategies, ensure adherence to all requirements and preparation of documents within required timeframe, scheduling efficient shipping and identify appropriate transportation method.
- Supervise efficient working of team, ensure compliance to all import objectives, design strategies for better output.
- Strong follow up from cargo handover to Shipping line / Air Line till delivery to end user.
- Monitor financial and currency transactions related to import and manage all communication with finance department and banks.
- Coordination with forwarders, clearing agents, visiting online customs & banks sites for continuous update on changing market dynamics and intelligence.
- Negotiates best rates with freight forwarders for international shipments.
   Search and add new agents / forwarders / consolidators to gain efficiency, reduce transit time and save cost.
- Elaboration of different reports to the management like weekly shipments and payments report, monthly budget,
- monthly expenses, annual data.
- Credit control of due invoices of associated agents, sorting payment related matters and building good relationship for productive business.



# Sr. Officer Imports Sitara Chemical Industries Limited Mar 2018 - Sep 2020

- Identify and evaluate potential suppliers and vendors.
- Negotiate terms and conditions with suppliers, including pricing, payment terms, and delivery schedules
- Select suppliers based on quality, cost, reliability, and other relevant factors.
- Create and manage purchase orders (POs) for goods and services.
- Analyze the costs associated with procurement and identify opportunities for cost savings
- Assist in preparing and reviewing import documentation, including invoices, bills of lading, customs forms, and import permits.
- Leading import team to carry out complete import process from shipment to deliver in warehouse.
- Complete working related to return of faulty and guaranteed parts to suppliers and then to import after repairing/replacement. Availing temporary import/export benefit to save cost.



## Sr. Supervisor Imports Interloop Limited Dec 2012 - Mar 2018

- Confirm all shipping details before allowing packages to leave facility and checking the accuracy of all documents before arrival of shipments.
- Pre-arrangements for custom clearance of import shipment and availing maximum benefits.(SROs).
- Nomination and follow-up of freight forwarder & custom clearing agents from handling to delivery of shipment.
- Nomination and follow-up of transporters for in-land transportation of shipments from port to warehouse.
- Maintained ongoing tracking information from shipment to delivery.
- Complete working of different SROs i.e. SRO 327, SRO 492, EFS etc.
- L.C opening, Amendment, Enhancement. Preparing documents for Advance, CAD and Open Account payments. Arranging Insurance memo of each consignment.
- Working for releasing I-Bonds used for different SROs
- Checking and supervision of bills of all service providers till payment.